Guide to the Harriet B. Hubbard papers, 1958-1978 MS2074
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Harriet B. Hubbard papers
1958-1978
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Hubbard, Harriet B.
MS2074
1 Linear Feet
Harriet Bissell Hubbard (1914-2005) was a Washington civic activist who worked more than six decades on preservation concerns. Collection documents her work inEducation; Children's rights, and Environment, ranging in date from 1958-78, with the bulk of material from the 1970s.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
Harriet Bissell Hubbard (1914-2005) was a Washington civic activist who worked more than six decades on preservation concerns. She was one of the people to help obtain passage of the 1950 Old Georgetown Act, which made the entire village a historic district. Hubbard was also involved with the Dupont Circle Citizens Association and fought against a plan to introduce a series of freeways across the city. Additionally, Hubbard was involved in environmental issues such as air pollution in DC and public land distribution as it affected DC public parks.
Hubbard served as chairman of the Education Committee. She also gave testimony and advised the DC Board of Education regarding the reorganization of DC's public education, in light of the consequences of the District of Columbia Self-Government and Government Reorganization Act in 1973, as well as the 1974 contract negotiations between the teachers union and the School Board, among other issues.
Harriet Hubbard was born in New York City and raised in Pittsburgh. She was a 1935 history graduate of Smith College and early in her career was a private secretary for author Theodore Dreiser.
Collection Scope and Content
The material is consists of one box, organized into three series, including Education; Children's rights, and Environment, ranging in date from 1958-78, with the bulk of material from the 1970s.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Education; Children's rights; and Environment.
Environmental issues; Education; Children's rights; Child welfare; Washington (D.C.); District of Columbia. Board of Education; Dupont Circle Citizens' Association; District of Columbia. Dept. of Recreation; Hubbard, Harriet B.
- Education, 1958-1976; MS2074 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of 12 folders of documents, reports, and contracts related to the Washington, DC educational system and Board of Education. The materials range from 1958-1976 and some items are in French, German, and Italian.
  - Report of Education Committee by Hubbard, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reorganization of Public Education, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Education, 1969-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Office of the Superintendent, 1968-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Regents, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contract Negotiations between the Board of Education and the Washington Teachers Union, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report of the Central Corridor Complex Committee on the establishment of a 4 year high school, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Translation of the Law in the Canton of Vaud related to vocational education, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Document on Social Promotion, Mainstreaming and Special Education, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter concerning homicide on the grounds of Francis Jr. High School, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Health Education documents in French, German and Italian, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Swiss Education Laws in French, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Children's Rights, 1975; MS2074 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series consists of 2 folders, "Child labor in the District of Columbia Act of 1975" and "Swiss guardianship Laws."
  - Child labor in the District of Columbia Act of 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Swiss guardianship Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Environment, 1962-1978; MS2074 Series 3; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series consists of 10 folders related to Washington, DC environmental issues. Topics include pollution, building codes and regulations, zoning issues, and property listings. There is also a folder on general air pollution in English, German, and French.
  - General information concerning air pollution documents in French, English, and German, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Information concerning air pollution in DC, 1970-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - DC Department of Recreation, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Various DC property listings, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - DC Zoning issues, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Building Codes and regulations, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Draft on the significant steps undertaken for cleaning the city, 1973 April (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - DC Park Land Agency, 1973 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Solid waste collection program in DC, 1978 May 02 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Offshore power systems, 1978 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 24)